A powerful true story of bitter revenge...
Breaker Morant is a drama, history, war film directed by Bruce Beresford.
During the Boer War, three Australian lieutenants are
on trial for shooting Boer prisoners.
Though they acted under orders, they are being used as scapegoats by the General Staff,
who hopes to distance themselves from the irregular practices of the war.
The trial does not progress as smoothly as expected by the General Staff,
as the defence puts up a strong fight in the courtroom.
Harry 'Breaker' Morant, played by Edward Woodward.
Major J.F. Thomas, played by Jack Thompson.
Cpt. Alfred Taylor, played by John Waters.
Lt. Peter Handcock, played by Bryan Brown.
Lt. Col. Denny, played by Charles Tingwell.
Cpt. Simon Hunt, played by Terence Donovan.
Breaker Morant is a 1980 Australian biographical war drama film directed by Bruce
Beresford, who also co-wrote the screenplay based on Kenneth G.
Ross's 1978 play of the same name.
It stars Edward Woodward as the title character, Lt.
Harry Harbord "Breaker" Morant, along with Jack
Thompson, John Waters, and Bryan Brown.
The film concerns the 1902 court martial of lieutenants Morant, Peter Handcock and George
Witton—one of the first war crime prosecutions in British military history.
Australians serving in the British Army during the Second Anglo-Boer War, Morant, Handcock, and Witton stood
accused of murdering captured enemy combatants and an unarmed civilian in the Northern Transvaal.
The film is notable for its exploration of the Nuremberg Defence, the
politics of the death penalty and the human cost of total war.
As the trial unfolds, the events in question are shown in flashbacks.
The film won ten 1980 Australian Film Institute Awards including: Best Film, Best Direction, Best
Screenplay, Best Leading Actor (for Jack Thompson) and Best Supporting Actor (Bryan Brown).
It was also nominated for an Academy Award for the Best Adapted Screenplay.
Breaker Morant remains the movie with which Beresford is most identified and has "hoisted the
images of the accused officers to the level of Australian icons and martyrs".
In a 1999 interview Beresford explained that Breaker Morant "never pretended
for a moment" that the defendants were not guilty as charged.
He had intended the film to explore how wartime atrocities can be
"committed by people who appear to be quite normal".
Beresford concluded that he was "amazed" that so many people see his film as
being about "poor Australians who were framed by the Brits".
The film explores themes of war crimes, writing,
mythology, south africa, military court.
The tone is emotional.